Thanks for the speech of the fourth debater of affirmative side.
感谢正方四辩的发言;
The contest has come to an end.
本场比赛已经全部结束;
Now all judges leave the site
现在有请各位;
and discuss the result, please.
评委离席合议;
So,
那个;
we firstly raise hands
要不然咱们先举手;
to vote.
投个票吧;
To Team AFF, raise your hand.
同意正方的举手;
To Team NEG?
投给反方的;
How about you two?
那您二位的意见是;
I haven't decided yet.
没想清楚;
They're equal.
很平均;
Yes. I also feel they're
对 我也觉得比较;
equal in strength.
势均力敌;
The contest was very interesting.
这场比赛确实很有意思;
Did you notice
你们有注意到;
when they got on the stage,
他们一上来;
they changed their order of seats?
就把辩位换了吗;
Why did they do that?
那这个是什么意思呢;
I probably
这个我大概;
knew what it meant
比赛看完的时候;
at the end of the contest.
我知道是什么意思了;
I'm familiar with these two teams.
这两支队伍我比较熟;
Here's the thing.
事情是这样的;
Team 235
二三五辩论队;
was in the same team with Team AFF.
跟正方本来是一支队伍;
Their relations are complicated.
他们的关系错综复杂;
The first debater of negative side
这个反方一辩;
is the girlfriend of fourth debater
跟正方四辩;
of affirmative side.
是男女朋友;
According to the format, the fourth debater
正方四辩按照赛制;
should refute the first debater.
要质询反方一辩;
He was afraid
他肯定又怕;
of his girlfriend and also wanted to win.
女友又想赢比赛;
So he changed seats with
于是就跟三辩换了;
the third debater
个位置;
to refute the second debater.
去质询对方二辩;
The problem was thus avoided.
回避掉了这个问题;
Team NEG had wanted to adopt
反方很有可能;
Tian Ji's strategy for a horse racing,
是想田忌赛马;
sacrificing the weakest player.
给软柿子让对方捏;
Unexpectedly,
没想到对方;
Team AFF did such a thing.
搞了这么一招;
So he had to also
于是他也只好;
exchange seats of the third and the fourth.
把三四辩调个个儿;
Which meant that
相当于又把;
the strategy of horse racing
田忌赛马的策略;
remained its advantage.
追回来一段;
That's how it goes.
就是这么回事;
Brilliant, brilliant!
厉害厉害厉害;
But anyway,
但不管怎么说;
from argument to refutation of Team AFF,
从正方立论到质询;
the only consensus Team NEG made
反方唯一确立的共识;
is the definition.
就是定义的共识;
They barely carried forward their argument.
论点基本没有推进;
My fellow debater,
请问对方辩友;
what's the usage of illness?
生病有什么用;
From another perspective,
换个角度可以;
illness can enhance our resistance.
增强我们的抵抗力;
My fellow debater,
那请问对方辩友;
what's the usage of looking for immortality?
求仙问药有什么用;
From another perspective,
换个角度可以;
it's good for self-cultivation.
修身养性啊;
My fellow debater,
那再请问对方辩友;
what's the usage of
每天无所事事 ;
staying at home,
在家发呆;
doing nothing at all?
又有什么用;
From another perspective,
再换个角度;
it can get over negative emotion,
可以消除烦恼 ;
and relax our body and mind.
放松身心;
So, from another perspective,
那所有有用之用;
are all useful things
换个角度;
also useless?
是不是也无用呢;
Useless things are useful,
无用之用有用 ;
and useful things are useless.
有用之用无用;
Your opinion is that
您方的观点其实;
you'll win anyway if you
就是换个角度;
change a perspective.
您就能赢呗;
Actually, our resolution
实际上我方辩题;
is a universal judgment.
是一个全称判断;
Okay. Let's look at the next
好 我们来看下一个;
question:
问题;
Is there any completely useless thing?
有没有完全无用的事物;
It's definitely a trap.
这完全是个坑啊;
Even if it's a trap,
但是是个坑你;
you have to jump into it.
也得跳进去啊;
Otherwise, you have to escape.
不然的话你就只能逃;
I think they could fight back.
我觉得可以刚回去;
Of course.
当然有;
Many scientific charlatans study perpetual motion machine.
很多民科研究永动机 ;
It's a useless thing to study it.
研究永动机就没什么用;
Studying perpetual motion machine
研究永动机;
is a useless thing.
这个无用之用;
Is it completely useless?
是不是完全无用呢;
See? You have to admit the opposite is right.
你看到最后还是得认嘛;
No.
没有;
Everything has its value.
万物皆有其价值;
So useless thing is also useful.
所以无用之用也有用;
Doesn't it illustrate
这不正说明了;
that
我方的论点;
our argument is right?
是正确的吗;
So useless thing
所以无用之用;
does not exist at all, right?
根本不存在 对吗;
Then what are we debating
那我们今天在辩论;
about?
什么呢;
If your argument
如果您方的论点;
stands,
成立的话;
the contest
这场比赛;
shouldn't exist, right?
也不应该存在喽;
It exists.
存在啊;
Uselessness of the useless thing
无用之用的无用;
is in a secular context.
是世俗语境下的无用;
When we talk about whether it's useful,
但是我们说有用没用;
we're judging its value.
判定的是其价值啊;
Things defined in a secular context
世俗语境下定义的事物;
are judged on their value,
对其价值的判断;
but you're always changing perspectives.
却在不断地变换角度;
Aren't you sticking to double standard?
您这难道不是双标吗;
Not bad.
还行;
Yeah.
嗯;
Not good.
不太行;
They only did half of the refutation and
他们反驳和归谬;
reduction to absurdity.
只做了一半;
She didn't pave the way
没给后续的;
for the first debater.
一辩铺平道路;
In my opinion,
但是我觉得呢 ;
in this round,
在这一轮;
she at least made audience think about
起码让观众去思考了;
several definitions of usage.
这几个用的界定;
So the purpose of this round
所以我觉得这一轮的;
has been reached.
目的达到了;
Task completed.
完成任务了;
It seems we won this round.
场面上算是赢了;
But we didn't press forward.
但还是没推下去啊;
The opponent responded too fast.
对方反应太快;
Even if we have time,
就算有时间;
we may not press forward.
也不一定能推下去;
Let's depend on Dango.
看团子的了;
Come on!
加油 ;
Let's welcome
下面有请;
the first debater of negative side to state the opinion.
反方一辩申论陈词;
Please.
有请;
Thank you, Chief Judge.
谢谢主席;
Hello, everyone.
大家好;
If a thing is useless to me,
一件事对我无用;
I'll call it a useless thing.
我便称之为无用之用;
The fellow debater would say:
然后对方辩友说;
No.
不对呀;
It is useful
它对我隔壁的;
for my neighbor.
李二狗有用;
Isn't it called useful?
这不就是有用吗;
It's the same as follows:
这等于是在跟你说;
Who told you dog food cannot be eaten?
谁说狗粮不能吃;
Dogs eat it.
狗就吃;
So dog food can be eaten.
所以狗粮能吃;
I admit it
我承认 ;
that humans can also eat dog food.
狗粮是人也能吃;
But we cannot regard it as our dinner,
但总不能当饭吃吧 ;
my fellow debater.
对方辩友;
Similarly,
同理;
from what perspective
换个什么角度;
can I enter a top university
可以通过让我看漫画;
by reading comic books
身心愉悦地;
in a pleasant way?
考上世界名校呢;
From what perspective
又换个什么角度;
am I guaranteed to
追星粉偶像;
make a living by worshiping idols?
可保我养家糊口呢;
These useless things
这些无用之用;
can be useful if we change a perspective.
换个角度都有点用;
But is that the exact usage that we
可它真的是我们需要的;
really need?
那个用处吗;
Just like us.
就像我们大家;
We debate together,
在一起打辩论;
eat together, hang out together,
我们一起吃 一起玩;
study in the library together,
一起在泡在图书馆;
and work all night long together.
一起通宵达旦;
We have become best friends.
我们成为了最好的朋友;
We have got
我们拥有了;
the best memories.
最美好的回忆;
But which team is not like this?
可哪支队伍不是这样呢;
Can friendship and memories
友情和回忆;
enable us to get
能够让我们拿到;
the trophy?
那座奖杯吗;
No.
不能;
You cannot win because of these
没有哪场比赛会因为;
in any contest.
这些判你赢;
We have to put in abilities
冠军只能用能力;
and efforts to be the champion.
和汗水来买单;
We're all ordinary people.
我们都是普通人;
What we need is to go to a college,
我们需要的是考上大学;
make a living,
是挣钱养家;
do things that are useful for us,
是做对自己有用的事;
and be a useful person.
是做一个有用的人;
Instead of saying
而不是嘴里喊着;
"the useless thing is the greatest usage"
庄子的无用之用;
written by Zhuangzi,
方为大用;
who finally lived a life
最终却把自己的一生;
as his pipe dream.
过成他口中的黄粱一梦;
Thank you.
谢谢;
Let's welcome
下面有请;
the fourth debater of affirmative side to refute.
正方四辩质询反方一辩;
The time limit is also two minutes.
时间同样是两分钟;
Thank you, Chief Judge.
谢谢主席;
Hello, my fellow debater.
对方辩友你好;
Hello.
你好;
Do you think
您方认为;
the standard of judgement
辩题中前后两个;
of usage in the resolution
有用与否的判断;
cannot be different?
标准不可以不同吗;
Of course no.
当然;
Otherwise, they would be
不然岂不是;
confused with each other.
张冠李戴了吗;
As for your argument,
所以您方的持方;
can I think like this?
我可否理解为;
Useless things
因为无用之用是;
are useless,
无用的;
so they are useless, right?
所以它就是无用的对吗;
Well...
这;
Circular argument.
循环论证了;
No.
不是;
According to
所以如果按照;
your definition,
您方的定义;
your argument is actually
您方的持方其实;
a nonsense.
是一句废话;
The key point of our argument is that
我方论点的关键就在于;
the usage of useless things is impractical.
无用之用就是不实用的;
Emphasizing their usage
非要强调它有用;
is a behavior
本身就是一种;
to abandon practicality.
抛弃务实精神的行为;
It will mislead many people's
这样会误导很多人的;
value judgment and behaviors.
价值判断和行为;
Give me an example.
你可以举个例子;
For students who are about to take college entrance examination,
比如即将高考的学生;
it's useless to read comic books every day.
天天看漫画就是无用的;
It's very realistic.
这是很现实的情况;
The question
这个问题;
has been answered by us
我方一辩早;
at the beginning.
已经回答过了;
On the contrary, in your notion,
倒是在您的观念中;
is there only one path for human life,
人生只能有一条道路;
or is there only one object
还是每个阶段;
in each period of life?
只能有一个目标呢;
Is my fellow debater's
对方辩友所谓;
so-called practicality
实用性的外表下;
packed with
是不是包裹着;
narrower values?
更加狭隘的价值观呢;
Thank you.
谢谢;
We failed this one.
没拿下;
As is expected.
意料之中;
It doesn't matter.
没关系;
Now it's the second round of speech.
下面是第二轮申论环节;
The second debater of affirmative side speaks,
由正方二辩申论;
and the third debater of negative side refutes.
反方三辩质询;
Anyhow, we wiped out
无论如何还是肃清了;
the opponents' battlefield.
对方的战场;
We won't be entangled with definitions.
下一步定义不纠结;
We'll see whose standard will win.
要撕个标准了;
They really have a fierce debate.
他俩说得有鼻子有眼的;
Did you understand it?
你听明白了吗;
Almost. Almost.
差不多 差不多;
Really?
真的假的;
Thank you, Chief Judge.
谢谢主席;
We just made a consensus.
刚才我们形成了共识;
Uselessness of the useless thing
无用之用是指那些在;
refers to that
世俗功利的;
in a secular context.
语境中没用的存在;
It has no problem at all.
这一点没有问题;
The problem is that
问题在于;
how we should
我们应该如何去;
evaluate the usage of useless things.
评价无用之用呢;
We think,
我方认为;
the standard of evaluation
评价的标准;
should be multi-dimensional.
应该是多维的;
In an avalanche,
如果说雪崩之下;
no snowflake is inculpable.
没有一片雪花是无辜的;
At the moment when people succeed,
那么在人生成功之时;
each book we read,
我们读过的每一本闲书;
each song we listened to,
听过的每一首音乐;
and each inch of land we walked by
走过的每一片土地;
are not useless.
都不是无用的;
Am I right?
不是吗;
When you use multi-dimensional standard
当你用多维的标准;
to evaluate the usage of useless things,
去评价无用之用;
you'll find out that
你会发现;
they'll always blossom
它们总能在一片;
into useful flowers
沙漠之中;
in the desert.
开出有用的花朵;
So, in our opinion,
因此我方认为;
useless things are useful.
无用之用有用;
Because this evaluation
因为这样的评价;
is more comprehensive,
才更全面 ;
more objective, and more equal.
更客观 更公平;
It won't lead us to
才不会让我们在;
arrogance and ignorance
功利主义的价值观下;
under the utilitarian value.
走向傲慢 无知的深渊;
From the second round,
从第二论开始啊;
Team NEG tried to fight back.
反方试图去反击;
Evaluation is multi-dimensional.
评价方式是多元化的;
I think this point
我觉得这个点;
has no problem.
没什么问题;
It would be argued as extreme.
马上就会被推极端的;
My fellow debater.
对方辩友;
Is the sense of right and wrong a kind of
是非观念是不是一种;
evaluation?
评价方式;
Yes.
是;
So is the evaluation of right and wrong
所以是非好坏的评价;
also multi-dimensional?
也是多维的吗;
Is the standard of right and wrong
对错黑白的标准;
not unique?
也不是唯一的吗;
Kidnapping with morality.
想用道德绑架;
You're right, my fellow debater.
对方辩友您说对了;
The standard of right and wrong
对错黑白的标准;
isn't unique, of course.
当然不是唯一的;
The hound is good for hunters,
猎狗对猎人来说是好;
but bad for rabbits.
对兔子来说就是坏;
The feudal etiquette
三从四德在;
was right in feudal society,
封建社会是对的;
but is definitely wrong nowadays.
在今天当然是错的;
The sun looks white with naked eyes,
太阳从肉眼看是白的;
but looks black in the camera film.
相机底片中便是黑的;
The world is complicated in nature.
世界原本就是复杂的;
Evaluation standard is also multi-dimensional.
评价标准也是多维的;
Any problem?
这有什么问题吗;
Don't be so aggressive!
大姐要不要这么刚啊;
Yes. So a thing
对 所以一件事情;
is both rational
你的角度我的角度;
from our perspectives.
都有其合理性;
Does it belong to
那到底这属不属于;
multi-dimensional standard?
多维标准呢;
Of course.
当然;
So each of us argues
这不就是公说公有理;
from our own perspective.
婆说婆有理吗;
How do you judge by
那请问这样的标准;
such standard?
如何做出判断;
What problems can you solve
又能解决什么样的;
with it?
问题呢;
It's tricky.
有点麻烦;
If there's no kindness, there's no evil.
没有善何来恶;
If there's no ugliness, there's no beauty.
没有丑何来美;
Evaluation can be multi-dimensional,
评价可以是多维的;
but it doesn't mean that
但这并不意味着;
we cannot
我们可以;
distinguish beauty from ugliness, right from wrong.
美丑不分 善恶不辨;
The evaluation of a thing
对一个事物的评价;
originates from its principal contradiction
来源于它的主要矛盾;
and principal aspect.
和主要方面;
That is the standard we need
这才是指导我们生活;
to guide our life.
应该有的标准;
My fellow debater, am I right?
对方辩友 我说得对吗;
From the beginning till now,
所以对方辩友从;
the opponents
比赛开始到现在;
are only doing one thing:
就一直在做一件事;
Giving useless things a value,
就是为无用之用上价值;
an unconvincing value.
而且是硬上价值;
If it's unconvincing, what value
如果硬来又有什么价值;
cannot be found?
是完全找不到的呢;
In 2016,
二零一六年;
a young girl
一个年轻女孩因为;
was obsessed with online novels.
沉迷网络小说;
She starved to death in the staircase
竟然捧着手机在;
with a phone in hand.
楼梯间饿死了;
If we must find the usage
如果硬要找网络小说;
of online novels brought to her,
对她带来的有用之处;
it probably made her
那大概只能是让她;
less painful
走的时候;
when she died.
很安详了吧;
This kind of usage
这样的有用;
can lead us to
除了让我们陷入;
the emptiness of values.
价值观的虚无;
What else?
还能有什么用呢;
We hope the opponents
我们希望对方辩友;
do not forget
不要忘记自己;
responsibilities as debaters.
作为辩手的责任和担当;
Don't forget the most
不要忘记辩论中最;
valuable spirit in debating:
最可贵的精神;
seeking for the truth.
求真;
A thing is as what
如果它是这样的;
it should be.
那它就是这样的;
If it's useless,
如果它是无用的;
please admit that it's useless.
那就请承认它的无用;
Thank you.
谢谢;
Thanks for the second debater's
感谢反方二辩的;
splendid speech.
精彩陈辞;
Let's welcome the third debater of affirmative side to refute.
下面有请正方三辩质询;
Please.
有请;
Thank you, Chief Judge.
谢谢主席;
Hello, my fellow debater.
对方辩友 您好;
Hello.
您好;
You have been saying that our
您方一直说我方的;
definition is not right,
定义不对;
and criteria is not standard.
判准不准;
But you didn't give us
可您方却没有给出;
your process of argumentation.
自己的论证过程;
Please give us an example
那就不妨请您举一个;
of uselessness
您方认可的无用;
that you support.
之用的例子;
So bold!
胆子真大呀;
Why?
怎么说;
During refutation,
他在质询阶段;
he completely hands in the opinion
完全把交锋点;
to the opponent.
留到对手上;
It means he's very confident.
说明他自己非常有信心;
If I were Hao,
那我要是小好姐;
I would delay the time
我就拖延时间;
by not responding him,
赖皮不回他;
so as to waste his refutation time.
消耗他质询时间 ;
Am I right?
对不对;
My fellow debater,
对方辩友;
that's why
这就是你为什么;
you're sitting as an audience.
一直坐在台下的原因;
If you go home on vacation,
比如放假回家;
you make a very busy
制定满满当当的;
study plan.
学习计划;
It's called a useless thing.
这便是无用之用;
Making study plan on vacation
放假制定学习计划;
can help me to study on vacation.
可以有助我假期的学习;
Isn't it useful?
这不是有用吗;
But you won't execute
但你根本就不会;
the plan at all.
去执行啊;
That's true.
就是;
So you mean that
所以您的意思是;
if I don't use it,
我不用的;
it won't be useful.
所以它就没有用了;
Aren't all skills
那不是所有的技能;
and knowledge
知识点;
useless if I don't use them?
我不用它它都没有用吗;
Can you give me an example
那您能举出一个;
that is useful even if
您不用它照样;
we don't use it?
有用的例子吗;
Of course.
可以啊;
One filled with knowledge behaves with elegance.
腹有诗书气自华;
It's useful even though we don't use it.
就不用也有用呀;
Filled with knowledge
腹有诗书的作用;
is useful for behaving elegance.
就是气自华;
Why is it called useless?
这怎么能是没用呢;
But it doesn't
但它并没有;
make a direct effect.
直接的作用啊;
So direct usage
所以直接有用才;
is called usage.
叫有用喽;
Knowledge that is not
那不是考试没有;
on the exam paper
考到的知识点;
is useless,
都是无用之用;
and we're just making useless efforts.
都白学了呢 ;
At least we should have a clear
至少要有明确的;
cause and effect relation.
因果关系;
Right?
才可以吧;
Otherwise it would come back to
否则不又回到了;
the endless loop
我方举个例子;
where I make an example
您方换个角度的;
and you change another perspective.
死循环上面来了吗;
Do you continue to deny
您方还要继续否认;
the existence of useless things
无用之用的存在;
and thus deny the resolution?
进而否认辩题吗;
Yes.
没错;
We support the definition
我们认可辩题中;
of useless things in the resolution,
对无用之用的定义;
which is the useless thing
就是在世俗功利中;
in the secular context.
被认为没有用的事物;
We also explicitly assert
可是我方同时也;
at the same time,
明确地主张;
that completely useless things
完全无用的事物;
don't exist.
根本就不存在;
It's also our
这也正是我方;
resistance and negation
对功利主义的;
against utilitarianism.
反抗和否定;
Because judging whether a thing
因为用功利主义的标准;
is useful or not with the standard
去判定一个事物;
of utilitarianism
有没有用;
is itself
这本身就是一种;
a prejudice and unfairness.
偏见和不公;
It's even a self-castration of
更是对我们人生选择的;
our choice of life.
一种自我阉割;
Countless choices that are useful
无数看似无用;
but we think are not
实则有用的选择;
are neglected, abandoned,
都在无用的判定中;
and buried
被忽略;
during useless judgment.
被抛弃 被埋没;
From this perspective,
从这个角度上讲;
we must deny
我们就是要否定;
the existence of useless things.
无用之用的存在;
In your opinion,
因为对方辩友口中;
the useless thing today
今日的无用;
may become useful tomorrow.
可能是明日的有用;
Nihility now
眼前的虚无;
is more likely to be the foundation
更有可能是构建;
for constructing the future.
未来的基石;
The ancient Greek rhetoricians,
正如古希腊先贤的思辨;
Owen in the eighteenth century,
十八世纪欧文;
and utopia of Saint-Simon.
和圣西门的空想;
They were all greeting
他们都在表面的;
the next era
无用之中;
in the atmosphere
迎接着下一个;
of uselessness.
时代的来临;
So, all that seem useless
所以 所有看似的无用;
are testifying the short-sighted people.
都在证明着目光的短浅;
We're inferior.
劣势了;
It's okay.
没事;
So fierce.
太狠了;
He really negated the resolution
居然真的从定义上;
on the definition.
否定了辩题啊;
More importantly, he made it reasonable.
这关键还合理化了;
If it continues, we have no way
这样下去咱们根本;
to beat them.
就没法打了;
The coach of Team NEG
反方教练;
applies for a tactical pause.
申请战术暂停环节;
This period lasts for three minutes.
本环节共三分钟;
It allows two coaches to be involved,
允许两队教练上场;
and adjust the team member and
根据上半场的赛况;
strategies according to
调整队员阵容 ;
the result of the former contest.
战术打法等;
Time begins.
现在计时开始;
Sorry. I made a mistake.
对不起大家 我失误了;
It's okay, Hao.
没事小好;
The argument did not collapse. We can beat them.
立论没崩 可以打;
Nan Bei. Are you on or not?
南北 上不上;
See you on the stage.
场上见;
Yes.
我上;
Replace me.
那你替我吧;
No.
不行;
I cannot resist them anymore.
我已经有点扛不住了;
But my condition now...
但我现在这个状态;
Hao, listen to me.
小好姐 你听我的;
I'm good at argument
立论我可以;
and refutation.
对辩我也可以;
But for the free debating,
但是自由辩;
we really need you to be the leader.
真的需要你来当旗手;
You can control the situation.
掌控局势的;
I'm really not good at it.
这个我真的不太擅长;
Alright.
好了;
Listen to me.
来 听我讲;
Don't be panic.
不要慌;
Not until the last minute
不到最后一刻;
can we know who's the winner.
鹿死谁手都说不定;
Dango is right.
团子说得对;
Nan Bei, you are the first.
南北你上一辩;
You are in charge of rebuttal.
攻辩你来;
Others prepare for free debating.
其他人准备自由辩论;
Any questions?
有没有问题;
No.
没问题;
Good job in the former contest.
上半场不错;
But it's not enough to use logic.
但仅仅打逻辑是不够的;
We should unfold
后面还必须要把;
the second argument
第二个论点;
even more in the next round.
进行更多地展开;
I doubt they have
我怀疑他们还有;
more arguments.
深层论点;
Don't let them elaborate.
不要让他们打出来 ;
Understand?
知道吗;
Coach. We have solutions.
教练 我们有对策;
I think we can beat them.
我觉得可以打;
It depends on you to make decisions.
这个由你们自己决定;
But remember.
但记住了;
Be responsible for your decisions.
要对自己的决定负责;
At present,
目前呢 ;
we are a little bit inferior to them.
我们确实是略处下风;
But consensus has been reached.
但是共识基本达成;
It doesn't matter during refutation.
质询劣势不重要;
What matters is that we should pull the opponents
重要的是把对方拉在;
into our own battlefield.
咱们的战场打;
Rebutter
攻辩;
of opponent is either Liu Yanze
对方不是刘彦泽;
or Yin Nan.
就是殷楠;
So don't rush.
所以千万不要急;
Remember to elaborate
切记 把咱们的;
our own arguments.
论点打出来;
Understand?
明白吗;
Yes.
明白;
Good.
好嘞;
Besides,
还有啊;
use short time for attack and defense.
攻防要注意短打;
Ding Li
丁力;
As for the free debating,
反驳战场这一块;
you help
你后期;
to push arguments forward at the end.
自由辩负责推一下;
Okay.
好的;
In free debating,
自由辩论;
all members defend and fight back.
全体防守反击;
For one target, which is
目标只有一个;
strengthen our arguments.
强化立论输出;
Tao Hao, you control the battlefield.
陶好稳定战场;
Xiaoyu, you stir things up.
小鱼带节奏;
Nan Bei, you make the last hit.
南北补刀;
Ma Nan
马楠 ;
You control your participation.
你要控制参与次数;
Add value at the end.
后半段上价值;
And state your closing argument.
进你的结辩;
Understand?
都听明白了吗;
-Yes.  -Yes.
明白了 明白;
Brilliant!
优秀;
In my opinion,
他们目前来看;
they have no strength to
应该是没有力气;
unfold their own arguments.
进行自己立论的展开;
They may try their best to
估计会全力;
refute our arguments.
反驳我们的论点;
At this time,
这个时候;
as long as arguments stand, we will win.
论点站住了我们就赢了;
Understand?
明白吗;
Yes.
明白;
Fighting!
加油;
Alright. Ready to get on the stage.
好了 准备上场吧;
Besides,
对了;
the surgery of our old coach
老教练的手术;
is very successful.
非常成功;
Xiaoyu, come on!
小鱼加油;
Now we'll start rebuttal.
接下来是攻辩环节;
A random debater of each team
双方任意辩手;
can start debating on the
就上述辩论内容;
above content.
进行攻辩;
Four minutes in total.
时间共计四分钟;
Please.
有请;
You said useless things are useful.
您方说无用之用有用;
By what way do they change
是通过什么方式变;
into useful things?
成有用的呢;
In different time, space
不同的时间空间;
and principal length to observe,
和主体长度下;
we'll find out
观察就会发现;
useless things are the most useful.
无用之用方为大用;
As the big tree seen by Zhuangzi.
正如庄子看到的那棵;
The big tree survived from
因为不能成材;
logger's axe because
反而在伐木者斧头下;
it was not good timber.
幸存的大树那样;
So is the nature of things
所以事物本身的特质;
objective
是自身具备的;
or subjective due to
还是由外界观察;
people's observation?
角度决定的呢;
Do things change
事物难道会随着;
with the change of
观察尺度的变化;
the scale of observation?
而变化吗;
Of course.
当然;
When I observe
当我在原子尺度下;
at the atomic scale,
观察的时候;
we can only see carbon.
只能看到碳;
When I go back to the macro scale,
回到宏观我才发现;
I find out it's actually a diamond.
那是一颗钻石啊;
It is the specific array of
是碳原子通过;
carbon atoms
特定的排列;
that forms a diamond.
才形成的钻石啊;
What I want to ask is
我想问的恰恰是;
what you said.
您方所说的;
In what way do the
无用之用是;
useless things
通过什么方式;
become useful?
才变得有用呢;
There is an inventor in Hebei Province
河北有一个发明家叫;
called Craftsman Geng.
手工耿 ;
He is specialized in inventing some
他专门发明一些;
completely useless things.
完全没有用的东西;
And thus he goes viral online
从而爆红网络;
and becomes a famous web celebrity.
成为顶级网红;
Isn't it the usage of
这不正是无用之用的;
useless things?
有用之处吗;
What if his inventions
如果他的发明全;
are all useful?
都有用呢;
It's not within the range of
那这就不在我们今天;
the resolution we discuss today.
讨论的范围之内了;
You dare not answer directly.
您不敢正面回答;
The inventions of Craftsman Geng
手工耿的发明;
make him famous
之所以可以让他出名;
because his inventions are useless.
正是因为他的发明没用;
Do you notice that?
所以您发现了吗;
The true value of useless things
无用之用真正的价值;
is exactly their uselessness, right?
恰恰在于其无用 对吗;
It's just its basic nature.
这只是它的基本属性;
Of course, we have to admit
我们当然必须承认;
the basic nature, right?
这个基本属性对不对;
Inventions of Craftsman Geng are useless,
手工耿的发明没用;
so they're useful.
所以它才有用;
Big trees have no usage for human,
大树本身没有作用;
so they're useful
所以它对自己的;
for their survival.
生存有用;
You feel happy to
读闲书看漫画;
read comic books
没有人来考你;
because no one tests you.
你才会觉得快乐;
If comic books were listed
而一旦把闲书漫画;
as the content of exams,
列入为考试的话;
they would become useful.
它就变成有用的了;
All usages of entertainment
所有的娱乐;
and relaxation
和放松的作用;
would be gone.
就没有了;
The study of basic science
基础科学的研究;
is not limited
正是因为;
because it has no clear
没有明确的实用性目标;
practical objectives.
所以才不会被局限;
And so we can unrestrainedly
我们才可以天马行空地;
explore the universe.
探索这个世界;
If the study of scientists
如果科学家的研究;
has to be useful,
一定要有用的话;
the study of basic science
那基础科学的;
would be lifeless at all.
研究也就毫无生机;
Therefore,
因此 ;
only when useless things are useless,
当无用之用无用时;
they are useful.
它便有用;
When they become useful,
而当它有用时;
they're useless. Right?
便无用了 对吗;
I doubt they have
我怀疑他们还有;
more arguments.
深层论点;
Don't let them elaborate.
不要让他们打出来 ;
Understand?
知道吗;
Coach. We have solutions.
教练 我们有对策;
I think I can beat them.
我觉得可以打;
So, do you admit the premise?
所以您承认这个前提吗;
I admit.
我承认;
So, if my fellow debater
所以如果对方辩友;
thinks the value
的价值;
is to regard useless things
必定要将无用之用;
as useful things,
评价为有用的话;
basically,
则从基础上;
you have dissolved
就已经瓦解了;
the possibility that useless things are useful.
无用之用有用的可能性;
Thank you.
谢谢;
Regarding them as useful things
如果评价为有用;
dissolves the foundation of usage.
则瓦解了有用的基础;
Interesting.
有点意思;
To be honest,
但说实话我觉得;
I didn't expect
没有想到他们;
they would go even deeper.
能推到这个层面;
Team AFF is so experienced.
正方很有经验啊;
In free debating,
自由辩论马上;
they fought back right away.
就开始反击了;
Next, it's the most anticipated
接下来就是大家最期待;
and the most exciting
最刺激的;
free debating.
自由辩论环节了;
Four minutes for each team.
每方发言时间四分钟;
Team NEG goes first.
从反方先开始;
Let's confirm the consensus.
确认一下共识;
The premise of usage is useless.
有用的前提是无用;
Do you admit it?
您方承认吗;
Yes.
承认;
But another consensus is
可另一个共识是;
the core of our debate,
我们辩论的核心;
which is how to evaluate useless things.
是如何评价无用之用;
Why don't we look at the result
评价一件事物;
but the premise
为什么不看结果;
when we evaluate something?
反而看前提呢;
Don't my fellow debaters
对方辩友难道;
look at the premise?
你们不看前提的吗;
What is final judgment?
什么叫盖棺定论;
We can only evaluate when there's a result.
有了结果才有评价 ;
Right?
不是吗;
History of Philosophy
哲学史这门课;
can be called a useless thing
从功利角度算是;
from a secular perspective.
无用之用了吧;
But countless wisdom it contains
但是它蕴含的无数智慧;
can be seen everywhere,
结晶在方方面面;
benefiting us a lot.
让我们受益匪浅;
Isn't it useful?
这难道不是有用吗;
Because it's not a practical subject,
正因为它并非实用学科;
it can be useful.
才可以做到这一点;
If it's targeted to practicality,
如果着眼于实用的话;
History of Philosophy would be called
那哲学史会被写成;
Useful Philosophy in Life,
生活中有用的哲学;
One Hundred Small Knowledge
小知识一百例;
or Business Expertise of
或者是维特克斯坦的;
Wittgenstein.
生意经;
Isn't your usage
那您方的有用;
greatly reduced?
是不就大打折扣了;
Useless things can help people to
无用之用对人生的;
accumulate and grow up.
积累和提升;
Aren't they useful?
难道不是有用吗;
Accumulation and growing up
人生的积累和提升;
are hard to be quantified.
很难量化;
How do you judge
您方又是如何判断;
whether they're useful or not?
有用还是无用的呢;
No matter how small accumulation and growing up are,
积累和提升哪怕很微小;
they're still useful.
难道就不是有用了吗;
My fellow debater.
对方辩友 ;
Don't do useless thing no matter how big it is.
勿以无用大而为之;
Don't stop doing useful thing no matter how small it is.
勿以有用小而不为啊;
What does she mean?
什么意思啊;
Yin Nan takes advantage of Xiaoyu,
殷楠占小鱼便宜;
asking Xiaoyu to call her dad.
让小鱼叫她爸爸;
The energy consumed by brain
人大脑消耗的能量;
takes 25% of the energy
占据全身的百分之;
consumed by the body.
二十五;
It's the most energy-consuming organ.
是耗能最大的器官;
According to what you said,
按照您这么说;
if I want to lose weight,
如果我想减肥的话;
it's also useful to do advanced mathematics exercises.
其实做高数也有用;
It consumes energy of the brain.
毕竟费脑子嘛;
Yes. So it's useful!
对啊 所以有用啊;
Although it's weak.
虽然很微小;
But doing exercises for a few days,
可是做题好几天;
you find out that
宅在桌边竟然;
you've gained one kilogram.
又胖了两斤;
Is doing exercises useful
做题这件事情对于;
or not
减肥来说;
for losing weight?
到底是有用还是无用呢;
A careless weed can make a shade.
无心插柳尚能成荫;
Isn't it the usage of
这不正是无用之用的;
useless things?
用处吗;
Good point.
说得好;
We plant carelessly because
无心插柳恰恰是因为;
we don't think it's useful.
我们不认为它有用;
So surprise will
意外和惊喜才会;
come, right?
到来不是吗;
After all, a careful planting cannot blossom.
毕竟有心栽花花不开啊;
Your first argument
您方第一个论点;
talks about practicality.
是讲实用性;
But now you talk about
现在却大谈对;
the resistance to utilitarianism.
功利主义的反抗;
Isn't it a self-conflict?
这不是自相矛盾吗;
How?
哪里矛盾了;
Are practicality and
难道务实和;
utilitarianism equal?
功利是等同的吗;
It's okay.
没关系;
At least we've reached
至少我们又达成;
another consensus.
一个共识;
We all think
我们都认为对;
the evaluation of useless things
无用之用的评价;
is against utilitarianism.
是反对功利性的;
But getting rid of utilitarianism
但对功利性的摆脱;
should rely on admitting value,
靠的应该是去承认价值;
instead of
而不是;
denying the value. Right?
否定价值 不是吗;
No.
不是;
Getting rid of utilitarianism
对功利主义的摆脱;
isn't to endow
不是去赋予;
utilitarianism with non-utilitarianism,
无功利的已功利;
but to admit that useless is useless.
而是承认没有就是没有;
Useful evaluation
有用的评价;
isn't to endow something,
不是强行赋予;
but that it really has values.
而是它真的有其价值;
It should be a question that
这应该是每一个辩手;
every debater has thought about.
都思考过的问题;
Because debate itself
因为辩论本身;
is a classically useless thing.
它就是典型的无用之用;
So how should we
所以我们要怎么样;
evaluate debate?
评价辩论呢;
Do we tell our juniors that debate is useless,
告诉学弟学妹辩论无用;
and recruit less members
然后坐等来年纳;
in the next year?
新雪上加霜;
Or do we tell our team members that
还是告诉队友们;
debate is useless,
辩论无用;
and let them lose morale
让他们在赛场上;
in the battle?
失去斗志;
Or do I tell myself that debate
抑或是我告诉我自己;
is useless,
辩论无用;
and deny my efforts and
然后否认我付出的;
sweats that I've made?
努力和汗水吗;
We can find out countless
我们可以为辩论;
useful points of debate.
硬找出无数个有用;
Training eloquence and thought,
锻炼口才 训练思维 ;
sportsmanship,
竞技精神;
etc.
等等等等;
Just like in this contest,
就像在这个赛场上;
your excellent knowledge and
你优秀的学识和;
adept skills
娴熟的技巧;
can always be used.
一定派得上用场;
So where on earth
那么到底用在;
are they used?
什么地方呢;
They are used to conquer the audience
肯定是征服观众 ;
and get the trophy.
获得奖杯;
See?
发现了吗;
You're used to
你们在习惯性地去;
looking for usage.
寻找有用;
Because usage makes people feel at ease,
因为有用才会让人安心;
and makes people feel that they have values.
让人觉得有价值;
If let us
那如果让我们;
try to forget all of these.
试着去忘记这些;
Forget the opponent,
忘记对手;
forget the audience,
忘记观众;
forget the trophy,
忘记奖杯;
and forget everything that is useful.
忘记一切有用的;
And think about
再想想;
what
是什么;
makes us prepare for the contest
让我们在狭小的;
in a small room.
房间里备赛;
What makes us quarrel
是什么让我们在;
all night long?
通宵达旦中争吵;
What on earth
让我们;
is it that is so charming to
东奔西走着奋斗的魅力;
make us fight for?
到底是什么呢;
There's only one question:
现在只剩下一个问题了;
Why aren't we willing to
我们为什么不愿意;
admit uselessness?
承认无用呢;
As what you said,
正如你们所说;
the evaluation of useless things
对无用之用的评价;
can truly affect reality.
会真实地影响到现实;
Is there
这两者;
any difference between them?
有什么区别吗;
Because we tend to choose
因为我们往往只会选择;
and care about those
和在意那些;
what we think are useful.
我们认定有用的事情;
We are born for benefits,
天下熙熙皆为利来;
and we would die for benefits.
天下攘攘皆为利往;
If we tell people
如果我们告诉大家;
the thing is useless,
这件事情无用;
not packing it or endowing it
不去包装和赋予;
with any usage,
它任何有用;
its value would be neglected.
其价值就会被忽略;
That is what we're worried about.
这才是我们所担心的;
For most of the people,
对于大多数人而言;
what on earth is the usage of useful things?
无用之用到底有什么用;
How much usage it has?
用处有多大;
It's hard to say.
真说不清;
But the nap of Newton under the apple tree,
但牛顿苹果树下的发呆;
the string of Einstein,
爱因斯坦的琴弦;
and the howling of Li Bai
李白豪饮高歌后的;
after drinking.
仰天长啸;
These
这些;
should not be neglected.
都不应该被忽略;
I know what you mean.
我明白你的意思;
From philosophy, arts, to personal interests,
从哲学艺术到个人爱好;
if it has a useful
如果它有一个有用的;
consensus,
共识;
it can make more people
就能让更多人;
to pay attention to it,
去关注它 ;
accept it,
接受它;
understand it, respect it,
理解它 尊重它;
and thus more free to
进而能够更自由地;
choose it.
去选择它;
We won't keep distance with something
不会因为某件事情无用;
just because it's useless.
就敬而远之;
If I didn't prepare for
如果不是因为准备;
the resolution,
这个辩题;
I would never know that
我都不会想到;
there are still people who
到现在还有人存在;
look down upon video games.
对电子游戏的歧视;
There're still many people who think
还有很多人觉得;
it's useless to learn Chinese opera
学习戏曲没用;
just because nobody listens it.
因为根本没有人听;
There are even some people
甚至还有某些人 ;
and some groups
某些群体;
believe that reading is useless.
信奉着读书无用;
Defending that useless things
为无用正名;
are useful
说它有用;
is to make useless things
就是为了让无用之用;
as part of our
成为我们自由;
free choices.
选择的一部分;
However,
可是;
there seems to be a problem.
这好像有点问题呀;
One has values only when it's deemed as useful.
被认定有用才会有价值;
One is worth choosing only when it's useful.
有用的才值得被选择;
Actually, the topic
其实这个话题;
is always very utilitarian.
一直非常有功利性;
But we haven't
只不过我们一直;
cared about it.
没有在乎到;
So we would feel anxious when we're
所以我们才会在娱乐的;
entertaining ourselves,
时候焦虑;
and blame ourselves at leisure time.
在休闲的时候自责;
Invisibly,
无形中;
each of us has strained our life
我们每个人都用有用;
with useful things.
来捆绑了自己的生活;
Only when we abandon usage,
只有放弃有用;
just like what we're doing now,
就像现在的我们;
only when we don't care about the contest,
只有不在乎这场比赛;
can we truly feel
才可以切身体会到;
the real value of the contest.
这场比赛的真正价值;
Admitting the uselessness of useless things
承认无用之用的无用;
is the biggest fight against
才是对功利主义;
utilitarianism.
最大的反抗;
Only when we're willing to admit
只有当我们愿意去承认;
one thing is useless.
一件事情无用;
When you dare to criticize
当你敢于去批判;
When you dare to respect
当你勇于去尊重;
And when you still choose
然后依然毫无顾及地;
and enjoy
去选择和享受;
the useless things
那所谓的;
without scruple.
有用无用的时候;
It's true freedom, isn't it?
才是真正的自由 对吗;
Right.
没错;
I hope we can all become
希望我们都可以成为;
the one
享受;
who enjoys useless things.
无用之用的人;
And it helps us to
而这恰恰能够帮助;
become
我们成为;
the most useful people.
最有用的人;
Alright.
好的;
Let's vote for the
那就为最终的;
final result.
结果投票吧;
Come on.
来;
To Team AFF, raise your hand.
投给正方的举手;
Alright. Say something.
好了 说两句 说两句;
Say something. Say something.
说两句 说两句;
Say something.
说两句;
Nothing to say.
没什么说的;
Act like a general.
拿出大将风范来;
It's time for the trophy.
时间不早了 领奖去;
Let's go.
走;
Come on! Let's go!
走 走走走;
They're becoming
越来越像;
more like a first-class team.
一支一流的队伍了;
Team 235, the Team NEG,
反方二三五辩论队;
is the champion of the provincial contest!
成为本届省大赛的冠军;
Congratulations!
恭喜;
The patient just sobered up.
病人刚清醒;
Be quiet.
你们轻点;
We're sorry.
不好意思;
Coach
教练;
How's the surgery?
手术怎么样;
Oh, right.
对对对;
Look at it.
看看 看看;
Coach. We won!
教练 我们赢了;
Coach. We avenged.
教练 我们报仇了;
But the revenge of Nan Bei
可是南北的;
hasn't be taken yet.
私仇还没报呢;
Coach. Thank you.
教练 谢谢您;
Coach
教练 ;
When will you regain your health?
你什么时候好啊;
When you recuperate,
等您好了;
let's eat hotpot together!
我们一起去吃火锅;
You are great!
你们都是好样的;
Congratulations!
恭喜啊;
Whoa!
哟;
You look so handsome
果然是人靠衣装啊;
with this suit!
是不一样;
Really!
真的;
You look like a graduate now.
是有点毕业生的样子了;
Thank you.
谢谢你们;
I really should express my
我真的应该;
gratitude to you.
由衷地感谢你们;
Wait.
哎;
Don't do that.
你别这样啊;
It's strange that you changed all of a sudden.
突然这样都不习惯了;
Right. Don't be so polite.
就是 客气什么呀;
I just want to thank you.
就是想谢谢你们;
If
如果;
it were not because of you,
不是你们的话;
I might
我可能;
still be playing video games at dormitory now.
现在还在寝室打游戏呢;
Especially,
尤其;
I'll thank Hao.
我要感谢小好;
Because...
因为吧;
Hao
小好姐;
Tao Hao, I want to...
陶好 我想;
Listen to me first.
你先听我说;
Mr. Li said
李主任说;
the grade of your computer science
你有一门计算机的成绩;
couldn't be found anyway.
怎么都查不到;
Computer?
计算机;
Yes.
对;
It's a new compulsory subject
就是今年新开的;
newly added this year.
一门必修课;
Mr. Li said he told you
李主任说开学;
at the beginning of the semester.
他就告诉你了;
You promised him that you would take it.
你答应他一定会去上的;
Did you take it?
你学了吧;
Man!
哎;
I thought everything's fine
我以为英语四级;
if I passed CET-4.
过了就行了;
Where does the computer emerge from?
计算机是哪儿来的;
Mr. Li said
李主任说;
the subject was newly added.
计算机是今年新加的;
All seniors
所有大四的学生;
have been informed.
全都通知了;
Maybe,
可能;
only you, the fifth year student, was missed.
就落了你一个大五的;
Will you blame me?
你不会怪我吧;
In your sixth year, there are 12 months.
你大六这一年十二个月;
If the salary is 6,000 yuan,
算月薪六千;
the total income of one year, reward added, is 76,000 yuan.
年终双薪就是七万六;
Half of it is to pay the debt. 38,000 yuan is left.
一半还房贷就是三万八;
After doing this math,
这么算下来;
if you do two part-time jobs every month,
你只要一个月打两份工;
you can earn 38,000 yuan.
就可以补上这三万八;
If you do this,
你要是这样的话;
I won't be angry.
我就不生气了;
Where's your Liu Yanze?
你们家刘彦泽呢;
Wasn't he like a chewing gum,
平时不是跟橡皮糖似的;
always sticking to you?
一直粘着你;
Why is he not with you today?
今儿没跟着你啊;
He said somebody suddenly looked for him.
他说突然有人找他;
I don't know who the person is.
我也不知道是谁;
Hey.
哎;
What are they doing out there?
那边干嘛呢;
So many people.
这么多人;
Someone's confessing love!
好像在表白;
Let's go and have a look.
走走走 去看看;
Wow!
哇;
Oh my god!
我的天哪;
The scene looks so spectacular!
可以啊这阵势 够壮观;
She will definitely succeed!
这阵仗 肯定没有问题;
Why? Like what you experienced before?
怎么 跟你当年一样;
Do you know her? Good friends?
你俩认识 姐们儿啊;
No.
不认识;
But browsed from the Internet,
但是现在百度;
every trick is like this.
随便一招都是这样的;
There has been no innovation
这么久了也没有;
for so long.
什么新意;
But the lady looks
不过这女的长得;
beautiful.
还倒挺好看的;
Where's the man?
男的呢;
Why haven't I seen him?
我怎么没看着呢;
I haven't, either.
没有看到啊;
My man!
我的男的;
Sorry, I have...
抱歉 我已经;
Hey!
哎;
I'm in charge of sanitation.
我是卫生委员会;
What are you doing?
你这干嘛呢;
Don't we need to clean up so many candles?
这么多蜡烛不需要扫啊;
Besides,
还有;
I'm Liu Yanze's
我是刘彦泽的;
girlfriend, Xiong Zishi.
女朋友熊子时;
To whom are you going to confess love?
你要给谁表白啊;
Sorry.
对不起;
What does that mean?
什么意思啊;
Explain it to me.
你给我解释解释;
I haven't been here for so long.
好久没来这儿了;
This time,
这次来;
the mood is totally different from last time.
跟以前心情完全不一样;
Mood is different.
心情不一样了;
But people are the same.
但人还是一样的;
Here you are.
给;
What is it?
什么;
When I hold exhibitions in the future,
等我以后办展了;
these are all my private treasures.
这可都是私家珍藏;
They're so valuable.
可值钱了;
When did you take so many
你什么时候拍我;
photos of me?
这么多照片;
No retouching!
修也不修;
You've been so beautiful.
本身都这么好看了;
No need to retouch!
还修什么呀;
How's that?
怎么样;
Stop!
你给我站住;
Nan Bei
南北;
How's that? Is it ready?
怎么样 弄好了没;
Right away.
马上;
Let me see it.
我看;
-Coach.  -Yes. The flight has been booked.
教练 对 机票都订好了;
Eat steamed pork stomach and chicken before departure.
临走吃一次猪肚鸡啊;
There's no such a dish in Europe.
欧洲没有那个东西;
Tao Hao. Ma Nan. Come over here.
陶好姐 马楠 快过来了;
Okay.
好;
I'm coming.
马上马上 ;
I'm making tea for our old coach.
我帮老教练泡茶呢;
We're coming.
来了来了;
Old coach.
来 老教练;
It's specially made for you.
特意为您泡的;
Thank you so much!
谢谢 谢谢;
Don't you need
你们这茶;
a cup of tea for each one?
是不是得一人一杯;
Nan Bei
南北;
Are you going to take with this?
你要用这个拍啊;
Yes.
对啊;
Let me tell you.
我告诉你;
You must PS the photo!
你可得把我修好看一点;
Of course.
妥妥的;
Wait me for a while.
你们等我一下;
You're here.
你来了;
It's a photo of your Team Two.
你们二队的合影;
Is it appropriate for me to be with you?
我来不合适吧;
Aren't you a family member of Team Two?
你不是二队的家属啊 ;
Come on.
来啊;
Come here.
来;
Wait a minute.
稍等啊;
Very soon!
马上;
Be closer. Be closer.
紧凑点 紧凑点 紧凑点;
Do I look good?
好看吗;
Yes.
可以吧;
Okay.
行了;
Alright. Be ready.
来了 准备;
Be ready.
做好准备;
Good, good.
可以 可以 可以;
Three seconds!
三秒啊;
Three, two, one. Cheese!
三 二 一 笑;
Let's go!
出发;